當我躺在退伍軍人醫院的時候
When I was lying there in the VA hospital,
人生猶如進入了空虛的大洞
with a big hole blown through the middle of my life,
我開始作起了飛行的夢
I started having these dreams of flying.
自由自在
I was free.
但你早晚會醒來
Sooner or later, though, you always have to wake up.
在冷凍期，你沒有夢
In cryo, you don't dream at all.
感覺不像過了6年
It doesn't feel like six years.
更像是喝醉酒，跟人幹了一架
More like a fifth of tequila and an ass-kicking.
湯米才是科學家，不是我
Tommy was the scientist, not me.
他才是那個 願意在數光年外找死
He was the one who wanted to get shot light-years out in space
只為找到真相的傢伙
to find the answers.
我們到了沒？
Are we there yet?
是的，我們到了
Yeah, we're there, sunshine.
我們到了
We're there.
是關於你哥哥的
It's about your brother.
那是在湯米 準備出航的一周前
So, a week before Tommy's gonna ship out,
有人給了他一槍 為搶他皮夾裡的鈔票
a guy with a gun ends his journey for the paper in his wallet.
你們在冷凍艙待了 五年零九個月又22天
You've been in cryo for five years, nine months and 22 days.
你們會感到飢餓和乏力
You will be hungry. You will be weak.
如果感到噁心，請用身邊的袋子…
If you feel nausea, please use the sacks...
是的，湯米才是科學家
Yeah, Tommy was the scientist.
而我，只是一個願意 替他去送死的傻瓜
Me, I'm just another dumb grunt going someplace he's gonna regret.
前方就是潘朵拉星球
Up ahead was Pandora.
小時候就聽說過 沒想到有一天自己會去
You grew up hearing about it, but I never figured I'd be going there.
你兄弟參與了一項很重要的投資
Your brother represented a significant investment.
我們想要你繼續他的合同
We'd like to talk to you about taking over his contract.
因為你們的基因相同 只有你才辦得到
And since your genome is identical to his, you could step into his shoes,
就像這樣
so to speak.
會是個在新世界的新開始
It'd be a fresh start on a new world.
而且報酬也很不錯
And the pay is good.
非常不錯
Very good.
- 戴上面具！戴上面具！ - 戴上面具！準備出發！
- Exo-packs on! Let's go! Exo-packs on! - Exo-packs on! Let's go!
大家記好了，一但失去面具…
Remember, people, you lose that mask,
20秒內你就會昏迷 4分鐘內你就會死去
you're unconscious in 20 seconds, you're dead in four minutes!
今天最好別死！ 會讓我的飛行記錄很難看
Let's nobody be dead today! Looks very bad on my report.
地獄門塔樓 TAV 1-6號正在靠近
Hell's Gate tower, this is TAV 1-6 on approach.
穿越外部標記，礦場就在眼前
Crossing outer marker. Mine is in sight.
一個生命結束
One life ends,
另一個就會開始
another begins.
摘下護帶！取好行李！
Harnesses off! Get your packs!
- 放在一起，準備出發 - 取下安全帶，一分鐘
- Put it together, let's go! Let's go! - Harnesses off! One minute!
通道降下後直接進入基地 別停留！
When that ramp comes down, go directly into the base. Do not stop!
直接進去，等我的指令
Go straight inside. Wait for my mark!
走，走，走！出發！ 開走！
Go, go, go, go! Get out of there! Keep moving! Let's go, let's go!
根本沒有「前軍人」這說法
There's no such thing as an ex-Marine.
你可以退伍 但是決不會失去軍魂
You may be out, but you never lose the attitude.
我告訴自己 別人能做到的，我也能
I told myself I could pass any test a man could pass.
只要你有錢，能治好殘疾
They can fix a spinal, if you got the money,
但在這個環境下 只靠退伍金可負擔不起
but not on vet benefits, not in this economy.
走吧，特殊個案 別讓我等你！
Let's go, special case! Do not make me wait for you!
好啊，小姐們
Well, well, ladies.
看看這些菜鳥！
Look at all this fresh meat!
在地球上 他們是保家衛國的軍人
Back on Earth, these guys were Army dogs, Marines,
為自由而戰
fighting for freedom.
當心，老爺車
Look out, hot rod!
但是在外面 他們只是僱傭兵
But out here they're just hired guns,
拿人錢財 替企業賣命
taking the money, working for the company.
看這個
Check this out, man.
輪子上一堆肉
Meals on wheels.
夥計，這不行吧
Oh, man, that is just wrong.
我這有兩個人有空！
I got two guys free in about 20 minutes!
收到！需要幫手！
Got it! Need them!
這裡不再是堪薩斯州
You're not in Kansas anymore.
你們處於潘朵拉，大伙們
You are on Pandora, ladies and gentlemen.
珍惜自己的每分每秒
Respect that fact every second of every day.
如果有地獄
If there is a hell,
待過潘朵拉以後 你寧願去地獄度假
you might want to go there for some R&R after a tour on Pandora.
在圍牆外面
Out there, beyond that fence,
每個生物 帶爪的，會飛的，泥潭的
every living thing that crawls, flies or squats in the mud
都想殺死你 把你的眼睛當菜吃
wants to kill you and eat your eyes for Jujubes.
這裡的土著居民叫納美人
We have an indigenous population of humanoids called the Na'vi.
他們有帶毒的弓箭
They're fond of arrows dipped in a neurotoxin
一分鐘就能要你的命
that'll stop your heart in one minute.
他們的骨骼 有天然碳纖維加固
And they have bones reinforced with naturally occurring carbon fiber.
很難殺死他們
They are very hard to kill.
作為安全主管 我要保障你們生命
As head of security, it is my job to keep you alive.
我做不到
I will not succeed.
如果沒有你們大家配合
Not with all of you.
如果想生還
If you wish to survive,
你們必須培養堅強意志
you need to cultivate a strong mental attitude.
必須遵守規定
You've got to obey the rules.
潘朵拉的規定
Pandora rules.
第一條…
Rule number one...
這像極了當年軍校的 宣講教條
There's nothing like an old-school safety brief
讓人倍感懷念
to put your mind at ease.
打擾一下，傑克！ 你是傑克吧，湯姆的兄弟
Excuse me. Excuse me. Jake! You're Jake, right? Tom's brother.
你倆長得真像
Wow! You look just like him.
抱歉，我是諾曼·斯柏曼 和他一起參加阿凡達訓練
Sorry, I'm Norm. Spellman. I went through avatar training with him.
...這是實驗室
...into the bio-lab.
我們將花大量時間在這 好嗎？我是諾曼，阿凡達駕馭員
We're gonna spend a lot of time up here. Hey! How you doing? Norm, avatar driver.
鏈接…這邊是鏈接室
Link... Here's the link room right here.
我們鏈接到阿凡達的地方
This is where we're connecting to the avatar.
我和諾曼就是到這來駕馭阿凡達
Me and Norm are here to drive
這些遠程遙控的身體
these remotely controlled bodies called avatars.
是由人類DNA和土著混合產生
And they're grown from human DNA mixed with the DNA of the natives.
- 歡迎 - 嘿
- Hey. Welcome. - Hey.
- 歡迎到潘朵拉，你能來真好 - 謝謝
- Welcome to Pandora. Good to have you. - Thanks.
靠！他們真大
Damn! They got big.
是啊，他們在運送途中成熟了
Yeah, they fully mature on the flight out.
催長液看來蠻有效
So the proprioceptive sims seem to work really well.
是啊，長得多健壯
Yeah, they've got great muscle tone.
你不知道運送他們多麻煩
It'll take us a few hours to get them decanted,
但你們明天就能用了
but you guys can take them out tomorrow.
那個是你的
There's yours.
你好，諾曼·斯柏曼博士
Hey. Dr. Norm Spellman.
- 邁斯博士，很高興見到你 - 很高興見到你
- Dr. Max Patel. Great to meet you. - Good to meet you, yeah.
真像他
Looks like him.
不，真像你
No, it looks like you.
現在是你的阿凡達了，傑克
This is your avatar now, Jake.
每個駕馭員都有自己唯一的阿凡達
And the concept is that every driver is matched to his own avatar,
他們的神經系統才能同頻
so that their nervous systems are in tune,
之類的
or something.
他們給我機會 因我能鏈接湯米的阿凡達
Which is why they offered me the gig, because I can link with Tommy's avatar,
而阿凡達造價極高
which is insanely expensive.
真可以嗎？ 我可以錄任何想說的？
Is this right? I just say whatever to the video log?
可以，我們要養成 記錄一切的好習慣
Yeah, we gotta get in the habit of documenting everything.
我們看到的，我們感覺的
You know, what we see, what we feel.
- 這就是科學 - 好的科學來源於好的觀察
- It's all part of the science. - And good science is good observation.
另外，接下來6年裡 還能讓你保持理智
Plus it'll help to keep you sane for the next six years.
好吧
All right. Whatever.
那麼…
So...
說到哪了
Well, here I am,
做研究
doing science.
他們出來了！
They're coming out!
注意，駕馭員脫離鏈接
Attention. Drivers coming out of link.
天啊
Oh, God.
試驗服在哪？ 試驗服在哪？
Where's the lab coat? Where's the lab coat?
誰拿著我的雪茄？ 這是怎麼回事？
Who's got my goddamn cigarette? Guys! What's wrong with this picture?
- 謝謝 - 格蕾絲·奧古斯丁是個傳說
- Thank you! - Grace Augustine is a legend.
她是阿凡達計劃的領頭人 她還寫了書
She's the head of the Avatar Program. She wrote the book,
親自寫下潘朵拉植物學著作
I mean, literally wrote the book on Pandoran botany.
那是因為 比起人類，她更喜歡植物
Well, that's 'cause she likes plants better than people.
她來了 灰姑娘從舞會回來
Here she is, Cinderella back from the ball.
格蕾絲，我給你介紹 諾曼和傑克
Grace, I'd like you to meet Norm Spellman and Jake Sully.
諾曼，我聽過你的事跡 你的納美語怎樣？
Norm. I hear good things about you. How's your Na'vi?
願全能的聖母…
May the All Mother...
…眷顧我們第一次的見面
...smile upon our first meeting.
不壞，還比較正式
Not bad. You sound a little formal.
我學了5年…
I studied for five years...
…還只初窺門徑
...but there is much to learn.
- 格蕾絲，這位是傑克 - 女士
- Grace? This is Jake Sully. - Ma'am.
行了，我知道你是誰. 我不要你，要的是你兄弟
Yeah, yeah. I know who you are, and I don't need you. I need your brother.
為這任務學了三年的博士
You know, the PhD who trained for three years for this mission?
他死了
He's dead.
我知道給對大家造成不便
I know it's a big inconvenience for everyone.
- 你進過多少次試驗室？ - 我解剖過青蛙
- How much lab training have you had? - I dissected a frog once.
看到沒？ 他欺負我們
You see? You see? I mean, they're just pissing on us
都不帶掩飾的
without even the courtesy of calling it rain.
- 我去找帕克 - 別啊，格蕾絲
- I'm going to Selfridge. - No, Grace,
- 我想最好別去 - 不行，這簡直是亂來
- I don't think that's a good idea. - No, man, this is such bullshit!
我必須去教訓他一下
I'm gonna kick his corporate butt.
他憑什麼插手我的部門
He has no business sticking his nose in my department.
明天早上8點到這 試著說好聽的
Here tomorrow, 0800. Try and use big words.
蠍子二號，這是塔樓 你可以從南方起飛
Scorpion Two-Hotel, Hell's Gate tower. You are cleared for south departure.
- 看到沒有？ - 是的，長官
- You see that? - Yes, sir.
胡說，你沒看 你在看顯示器
No, you didn't. You were looking at the monitor.
我愛這根桿！ 我愛死它了！
I love this putter, Ronnie! I love this putter.
帕克，我以為你是疏忽
Parker, you know, I used to think it was benign neglect,
現在我知道你是故意破壞我
but now I see that you're intentionally screwing me.
格蕾絲，我喜歡和你談話
Grace, you know, I enjoy our little talks.
我要研究員 不是退伍大兵
I need a researcher. Not some jarhead dropout.
其實，我覺得找到他滿走運的
Well, actually, I thought we got lucky with him.
- 幸運？ - 是啊
- Lucky? - Yeah.
這還談得上走運？
How is this in any way lucky?
走運的是 還有個雙胞胎
Lucky your guy had a twin brother,
而且走運的是 他兄弟不是個小白臉
and lucky that brother wasn't some oral hygienist or something.
我們需要個軍人
A Marine we can use.
我派他去給你做護衛
I'm assigning him to your team as security escort.
我最不需要的 就是亂開槍的白癡
The last thing I need is another trigger-happy moron out there!
你看 你的任務是贏得土著人的心
Look, look, you're supposed to be winning the hearts
還有他們的信任
and the minds of the natives.
這難道不是你的公仔戲？
Isn't that the whole point of your little puppet show?
外表像他們，說話像他們
If you look like them and you talk like them,
就能贏得信任
then they'll start trusting us.
我們建了學校，教他們英語
We build them a school, we teach them English,
但是過了多久？
but after, what, how many years?
雙方的關係越來越惡化
Relations with the indigenous are only getting worse.
當你用機關鎗 就有這結果
Yeah, that tends to happen when you use machine guns on them.
好吧，過來這
Right. Come here.
我不能…
I can't... I can't...
這是我們來的原因： 「鎢氪取」礦石
This is why we're here. Unobtanium.
因為這灰石頭能賣兩千萬每克
Because this little gray rock sells for 20 million a kilo.
因為這 才有人給我們投資
That's the only reason. It's what pays for the whole party.
才有人贊助你的研究
It's what pays for your science.
現在那些野蠻人 危脅到我們整個行動
Now, those savages are threatening our whole operation,
戰爭一觸即發
we're on the brink of war,
你的任務是尋求外交解決
and you're supposed to be finding a diplomatic solution.
用你手頭上的資源 給我點結果
So use what you've got, and get me some results.
你有過多少鏈接時間？
So, how much link time have you logged?
- 大概520小時 - 很好
- About 520 hours. - That's good.
你在這邊 你在這裡，你呢，多少時間？
You're in there. You're here. How much have you logged?
零，但我讀過說明
Zip. But I read a manual.
你開玩笑吧
Tell me you're joking.
真是酷
This is cool.
我們走
Let's go.
不用，我自己來
Don't. I got this.
你把自己放到這裡
So you just figured you'd come out here,
這個對人類最危險的環境
to the most hostile environment known to man,
聽天由命？
with no training of any kind, and see how it went?
你腦子在想什麼？
What was going through your head?
也許我聽膩了 醫生說我什麼不能做
Maybe I was sick of doctors telling me what I couldn't do.
- 生物統計正常 - 3個鏈接就緒
- Biometrics are good. - Link three is ready.
手放進去，低頭
Keep your arms in, hands in, head down.
低頭，放輕鬆 腦袋放空白
Down. Just relax and let your mind go blank.
這對你不難
That shouldn't be hard for you.
親我的菊花…
Kiss the darkest part of my lily white...
開始鏈接
Initiate link.
開啟三號序列
Run sequence unit three. Go.
啟動
Launching.
已經有一部同頻
I have the first congruency.
- 漂亮的大腦，多麼活躍 - 走著瞧
- That's a gorgeous brain. Nice activity. - Go figure.
40%分層鎖定
Phase-lock 40%.
好的，進去了
All right. Going in.
我從四號進入
I'm going in in four.
99%分層鎖定，鏈接平穩
Phase-lock 99%. Link is stable.
他來了，聽得見嗎？ 聽見我嗎，傑克？
He's in. Jake, can you hear me? Can you hear me, Jake?
瞳孔反應很好
Pupillary reflex is good.
聽力正常 你感覺怎麼樣？
Pinna response normal. How you feeling, Jake?
你們好
Hey, guys.
歡迎到你的新身體，傑克
Welcome to your new body, Jake.
好！
Good!
我們一步步來，傑克
Yeah, we're gonna take this nice and easy, Jake.
- 拇指觸摸指頭 - 好
- And touch your thumb to your fingers. - Yeah.
- 拇指觸摸指頭 - 沒問題
- Thumb to your fingers. - No problem.
很好，你還記得這個
That's good. I can see you can remember that one.
- 沒事 - 如果你想起來
- Got it. - Well, if you want to sit up,
- 沒有問題 - 好的，來吧
- that's fine. - Okay, good. Just take it
慢慢起來，傑克 身體協調正常，很好
nice and slow, Jake. Good. Okay, well, no truncal ataxia, that's good.
有沒有任何不適？ 你在動腳指頭！
Are you feeling lightheaded or dizzy at all? You're wiggling your toes!
- 好，好，傑克 - 很不錯
- Good. Good, Jake. - That's great.
肢端控制正常，很好
Distal motor control is good. Good, Jake.
有沒有疼痛麻木的感覺
Are you feeling any numbness or pain?
很不錯，傑克，等一等
That's great, Jake. Hold on, now.
別緊張 不要太心急
Take it easy. Don't get ahead of yourself, okay?
還有幾項反應測試
There's a few more sensory motor reflex tests we need to run,
- 別著急 - 等等
- so take it easy. - Wait.
- 傑克 - 坐下，傑克
- Jake. - Sit down, Jake.
傑克，聽我說
Jake! Listen to me. Jake!
- 我要你坐下，傑克 - 沒關係
- I need you to sit down. Jake! - It's okay.
- 夥計，聽我說 - 一切正常，我能行
- Buddy, listen to me. - It's all good. I got this.
- 傑克，你需要坐下 - 大伙把他拉回來
- Jake, you need to sit down right now. - Guys, get him back on the gurney now.
聽著，為了你的安全，先坐下
Listen to me. For your own safety, you need to sit down.
阿凡達需要時間適應 傑克
You need time to adjust to the avatar... Whoa! Jake!
- 天啊，傑克小心尾巴 - 好棒
- God, Jake, watch your tail. - Yeah!
鎮靜劑！一千毫克的鎮靜劑！
Sedate! Sedate him! A thousand milligrams of Supitocam! Stat!
夥計，夥計
Guys! Guys! Whoa! Whoa!
- 傑克，別這樣 - 聽我說
- Jake. Come on. - Jake! Listen to me.
你不適應阿凡達
You're not used to your avatar body.
- 這很危險 - 這很棒！
- This is dangerous. - This is great.
- 傑克？聽我說 - 別這樣，他們會把你放倒
- Jake? Jake, listen to me. - Come on. They're gonna put you out.
- 諾曼，坐下 - 不行，我要取下這些線
- Norm, sit down. - No, no. I gotta get out of these leads.
我的天，帶他們回來
God damn it! Bring them home!
- 諾曼，不許離開控制 - 你還沒準備好
- Norm! Do not leave control! - You're not ready for it!
- 來啊，你不會沒種吧？ - 差一點
- Oh, come on, you ain't got no skills. - So close!
我甚至不用防守
I don't even have to play defense on it.
你好，夥計們
Hey, guys. Hey.
- 沒事，我來抓他 - 傑克，你必須回去
－It's okay, I'll get him. - Jake, you have to come back!
傑克！等等
Jake! Jake! Excuse me.
- 小心 - 抱歉
- Watch it! - Sorry!
來吧！
Come on!
傑克！不允許我們跑步的
Jake! We're not supposed to be running!
- 天啊，對不起 - 注意點！
- Jeez! Sorry. - Watch it!
你好，大兵
Hey, Marine!
該死
Damn.
- 格蕾絲？ - 你以為呢？
- Grace? - Well, who'd you expect, numbnuts?
接住
Think fast.
反應還可以
Motor control's looking good.
大家靜下來，熄燈
Come on, everybody, quiet down! All right, gang, lights out.
來吧，路易斯，睡吧
Come on, Louise, chop-chop.
別搗鼓那個，你會瞎的
Don't play with that, you'll go blind.
這真怪異
That's kind of freaky.
好了，斯科特
Come on. Scat.
晚安
Good night.
熄燈！晚餐見，孩子們
Lights out! See you at dinner, kiddies.
歡迎回來
Welcome back.
- 你還好吧？ - 嗯，還好
- You okay? You all right? - Yeah, I'm okay.
我叫楚蒂，負責科研飛行 這是我的寶貝
I'm Trudy. I fly all the science sorties. And this here is my baby.
等等
Hold on a second.
威夫力，搞好它
Hey, Wainfleet! Get it done!
- 我們9點出發 - 交給我吧，上尉
- We bounce at zero-nine. - Yeah, I'm on it, capitaine!
重機槍還有點鬆
Vine strike's still loose.
你們的武器還挺厲害
You guys are packing some heavy gear.
小心
Watch it!
是啊，因為天空中不只有我們
Yeah, that's 'cause we're not the only thing flying around out there.
有更大的
Or the biggest.
我需要你控制艙門槍 人手不夠
I'm gonna need you on a door gun. I'm a man short.
還以為你不會提
I thought you'd never ask.
那是你要的人 起飛再見
There's your man. See you on the flight line.
你想見我，上校？
You wanted to see me, Colonel?
低引力會讓你軟弱
This low gravity'll make you soft.
一旦你軟弱
You get soft,
潘朵拉會立刻要你的命
Pandora will shit you out dead with zero warning.
我看了你的檔案，下士
I pulled your record, Corporal.
委內瑞拉，那裡很艱苦
Venezuela, that was some mean bush.
但也比不上這
Nothing like this here, though.
你很有種，小子 敢到這裡來
You got some heart, kid, showing up in this neighborhood.
我想只不過是另一個地獄
I figured it's just another hellhole.
我也曾是第一偵查隊
I was First Recon myself.
在你前幾年 或者不止幾年
A few years ahead of you. Well, maybe more than a few.
去三趟尼日利亞，沒留一點傷
Three tours Nigeria, not a scratch.
結果到這裡？
I come out here?
第一天，就像新入伍一樣
Day one. Think I felt like a shavetail louie?
是啊，如果我回去 能治好這些
Yeah. They could fix me up, if I rotated back.
讓我看起來更帥 但知道嗎？我喜歡這樣
Yeah, and make me pretty again. But you know what? I kind of like it.
能每天提醒我 外面都有些什麼
It reminds me every day what's waiting out there.
阿凡達計劃就是個笑話 一群娘娘腔科學家搞的
The Avatar Program is a bad joke. Bunch of limp-dick science majors.
不過，也算創造了機會 時間上，還有這次
However, it does present an opportunity both timely and unique.
一個陸戰隊員在阿凡達裡 多怪的組合
A recon gyrene in an avatar body. That's a potent mix.
讓我起雞皮疙瘩
Give me the goose bumps.
這樣的人，能提供給我
Such a Marine could provide the intel I need,
地面上的內部情報
right on the ground.
就在敵人內部
Right in the hostiles' camp.
聽著，傑克 我要你從內部學習這些野人
Look, Sully. I want you to learn these savages from the inside.
我要你取得他們信任
I want you to gain their trust.
我要知道怎麼逼他們合作
I need to know how to force their cooperation
或者怎麼滅掉他們
or hammer them hard if they won't.
- 我還跟格蕾絲博士一起？ - 表面上
- Am I still with Augustine? - On paper.
你裝成那群科學家一樣
Yeah, you walk like one of her science pukes, you quack like one,
但是對我匯報
but you report to me.
能幫我這個忙嗎？
Can you do that for me, son?
好的，長官
Hell, yeah, sir.
那就好
Well, all right, then.
小子，我會照顧自己人
Son, I take care of my own.
你幫我幹活
You get me what I need,
回去後我幫你找回雙腿
I'll see to it you get your legs back when you rotate home.
你自己的腿
Your real legs.
聽著真不錯，長官
That sounds real good, sir.
- 鏈接就緒！ - 分層鎖40%
- Link's ready! - Phase-lock 40%.
閉上你的嘴 讓諾曼來交涉
Just keep your mouth shut and let Norm do the talking.
5個同頻完畢，分層鎖90%
I have five congruencies. Phase-lock 90%.
鏈接三就緒
Link three ready.
好的，我來了
All right, I'm going in.
關上它，我們要停留一會
Shut it down. We're gonna stay a while.
- 諾曼！你的背包 - 背包
- Norm! Your pack. - Pack.
留在這裡 一個拿槍的白癡就夠了
Stay with the ship. One idiot with a gun is enough.
你說了算，博士
You the man, Doc.
潘狐猴，沒有攻擊性
Prolemuris. They're not aggressive.
放鬆，大兵，你讓我緊張
Relax, Marine. You're making me nervous.
他們怎麼知道我們來了
So, how will they know we're here?
他們肯定注視著我們
I'm sure they're watching us right now.
- 別停下，諾曼 - 大家跟上
- Keep moving, Norm. - Keep up, guys!
- 我來了 - 掃瞄
- And here I go. - Scanning.
這麼快？
Wow! It's that fast?
- 很神奇，不是嗎？ - 是啊
- Amazing, isn't it? - Yeah.
原來這是個信號轉換
So, that is signal transduction from this root
從這個根部到另一個根部 我們取個樣本
to the root of the tree next to it. So, we should take a sample.
好的，樣本
Okay. Sample.
這可能是基於反射速度的電子信號
You know, it's probably electrical, based on the speed of the reaction.
諾曼，你在用口水污染樣本
Norm, you've contaminated the sample with your saliva.
對喔
Right.
我動手了
So, here I go.
別開槍 你只會惹怒它
Don't shoot. Don't shoot, you'll piss him off.
他已經發怒了
It's already pissed off.
傑克，它鎧甲太厚了 相信我
Jake, that armor's too thick. Trust me.
它感到領地的威脅 別跑，不然它會衝來
It's a territorial threat display. Do not run, or he'll charge.
那我怎麼辦，請它跳舞
So, what do I do, dance with it?
站著別動
Just hold your ground.
是嗎？來啊！沒有種？
Yeah? Come on! What you got?
害怕了？這就對了
Oh, yeah. Who's bad? That's right.
知道我是誰了吧，爛貨
Yeah, that's what I'm talking about, bitch.
對了 回去找媽媽安慰就對了
That's right, get your punk ass back to mommy.
是啊，你個孬種 繼續跑啊
Yeah? Yeah, you got nothing. You keep running.
下次要不再多帶點朋友來？
Yeah, and why don't you bring back some of your friends, huh?
該死
Oh, shit.
這回怎樣？ 跑不跑？
So what about this one? Run? Don't run? What?
跑！快點跑！
Run! Definitely run!
要回去了，夥計們
I'm gonna have to call it, guys.
上校規定 不許夜晚行動
We're not allowed to run night ops. Colonel's orders.
抱歉，博士 他只能撐到明早了
I'm sorry, Doc, he's just gonna have to hang on till morning.
他不可能撐到早上
He won't make it till morning.
我沒時間陪你
I don't have all goddamn night.
來啊！上啊！
Come on! Come on!
等等，不要！
Hey, wait. Don't!
棒極了
Great.
你可能聽不懂
Look, I know you probably don't understand this,
但還是要謝謝
but thank you.
謝謝你
Thank you.
大開眼界
That was pretty impressive.
如果沒有你 我可能早死翹翹了
I would have been screwed if you hadn't come along. It was...
等一會，你去哪？
Hey, wait a second. Hey, where you going?
等等我
Wait up!
慢點
Just... Hey, slow down.
等等，我只想說 謝謝 幫我殺了那些東西
Look, wait up, I just wanted to say thanks for killing those things.
- 靠！ - 別謝
- Damn! - Don't thank.
你不要為這感謝
You don't thank for this.
這很悲傷，只有悲傷
This is sad. Very sad only.
好吧，對不起
Okay. Okay. I'm sorry.
不管怎樣，對不起了
Whatever I did, I am sorry.
都是你的錯 他們本不會死
All this is your fault. They did not need to die.
我的錯？被襲擊那個是我 壞人也是我？
My fault? They attacked me. How am I the bad guy?
你的錯！
Your fault!
- 你的錯！ - 冷靜，冷靜
- Your fault! - Easy. Easy.
你像個嬰兒 亂七八糟，不知所謂
You're like a baby. Making noise, don't know what to do.
冷靜
Easy.
好吧，好吧
Fine. Fine.
如果你這麼愛它們
If you love your little forest friends,
為何還要救我？
why not let them just kill my ass?
你怎麼想？
What's the thinking?
- 為何救你？ - 是啊，為什麼救我？
- Why save you? - Yeah. Yeah, why save me?
你有顆堅強的心
You have a strong heart.
不懼怕
No fear.
但很愚蠢！像嬰兒般無知
But stupid! Ignorant like a child.
如果我這麼無知…
Well, if I'm like a child, then...
你可以教教我
Look, maybe you should teach me.
天空人學不會 你們不看
Sky People cannot learn. You do not See.
那就教我看
Well, then teach me how to See.
沒人能教你看
No one can teach you to See. - Whoa.
聽著，我們不能聊聊？
Look, come on, can't we talk?
比如，你從哪學的英語？ 格蕾絲博士的學校？
Say, where'd you learn to speak English? Dr. Augustine's school?
你就像個嬰兒
You're like a baby.
我需要你幫忙
I need your help.
你不該來這
You should not be here.
- 那就帶我走 - 不，回去
- Okay, take me with you. - No! Go back.
不
No.
回去
Go back.
不！
No!
啥…
What...
這是什麼？
What are they?
聖樹的種子
Seeds of the Sacred Tree.
純粹的精靈
Very pure spirits.
這是為什麼？
What was that all about?
來
Come.
來！
Come!
我們去哪裡？
Where are we going?
來
Come.
你叫什麼名？
What's your name?
靠！
Shit!
好吧
Okay.
冷靜，大家冷靜
Calm people, calm.
你在幹嘛，蘇泰
What are you doing, Tsu'tey?
這兒禁止惡魔
These demons are forbidden here.
有啟示
There has been a sign.
而且這是巫后決定的事
This is a matter for the Tsahik.
帶他走
Bring him.
發生什麼事？
What's going on?
等等
Wait.
怎麼回事？
What's happening?
嘿！
Hey!
父親…
Father...
…我敬愛你
...I see you.
這生物…
This creature...
…為何帶他到這？
...why do you bring him here?
我原想殺他…
I was going to kill him...
…但遇到伊娃的啟示
...but there was a sign from Eywa.
我說過…
I have said...
…不許夢行人進來
...no dreawalker will come here.
他說什麼？
What's he saying?
他的異族氣味直熏鼻子
His alien smell fills my nose.
喂，他說什麼？
Hey, what's he saying?
父親在決定是否處決你
My father is deciding whether to kill you.
你父親，很高興見到你
Your father. It's nice to meet you, sir.
退後！
Step back!
我來看看這異族人
I will look at this alien.
這是我母親
That is Mother.
她就是巫后 她能預測伊娃的意志
She is Tsahik. The one who interprets the will of Eywa.
誰是伊娃？
Who's Eywa?
你的名字？
What are you called?
傑克
Jake Sully.
- 你為何來此？ - 我來此學習
- Why did you come to us? - I came to learn.
我們試過教別的天空人
We have tried to teach other Sky People.
杯已滿則水難進
It is hard to fill a cup which is already full.
我的杯子絕對空，相信我
Well, my cup is empty, trust me.
不信問問格蕾絲博士 我不是科學家
Just ask Dr. Augustine. I'm no scientist.
你是什麼？
What are you?
我是軍人
I was a Marine. A...
鍋蓋頭部落的戰士
A warrior of the Jarhead clan.
戰士
A warrior!
我能隨便殺死他
I could kill him easily!
我能輕易殺死他！ 不！
I could kill him easily! No!
這個是我們見到的…
This is the first warrior dreawalker...
…第一個夢行人戰士
...we have seen.
我們要研究他
We need to learn more about him.
我的女兒…
My Daughter...
…就由你…
...you will teach him our way...
…把我族的行為教給他
...to speak and walk as we do.
為何是我？不公平…
Why me? That's not fair...
已經決定 由我女兒傳授你我族之道
It is decided. My daughter will teach you our ways.
好好學，傑克
Learn well, Jakesully.
然後我們再看 能否治癒你的瘋疾
Then we will see if your insanity can be cured.
晚上好
Good evening.
不用起來
Please don't get up.
打擾一下
Excuse me.
抱歉
Sorry.
你好嗎？
Hey, how you doing?
- 傑克，傑克！ - 他在一號機
- Jake. Jake! - He's in alpha.
- 他正在出來 - 傑克！
- He's coming out right now. - Jake. Jake!
加把勁，孩子，做得好
Come on back, kid. Come on. That's it.
回來了，回來了
There you go. There you go, there you go.
你沒事了，沒事了
You're okay. You're okay.
嚇死我了 你眨眼快得像鐘擺
Damn! You were dug in like a tick.
- 你的阿凡達可好？ - 還好，博士
- Is the avatar safe? - Yeah, Doc.
你不會相信我去了哪
And you are not gonna believe where I am.
我們最後看到的 是大兵的屁股…
The last thing we see is this Marine's ass
消失在灌木叢裡 後面還追了只閃雷獸
disappearing into the brush with this angry thanator coming after him.
- 這種巧事，沒什麼經驗可說 - 太棒了
- Hey, it's not something you can teach. - That is awesome.
不知道什麼原因
You know, for reasons I cannot fathom,
奧馬地卡雅族選擇了你 上帝保佑
the Omaticaya have chosen you. God help us all.
「鍋蓋頭部落」？
"Jarhead clan"?
- 真的成功了？ - 我基本上是家族一員了
- And it worked? - Hey, I'm practically family.
他們要研究我 我必須學會融入他們
They're gonna study me. I have to learn to be one of them.
這是好的開始，小子
That's called taking the initiative, son.
- 再來10個你這樣的就好了 - 聽著，傑克
- I wish I had 10 more like you. - Look, Sully. Sully.
要找出那群藍猴子要什麼
Just find out what the blue monkeys want.
我們提供給他們 醫藥，教育，道路
You know, I mean, we try to give them medicine, education, roads.
但他們寧可選擇泥巴
But no, no, no, they like mud.
更煩人的就是…
And that wouldn't bother me, it's just that they're...
來人幫個忙，12區
Hey, can you... Can somebody just... Sector 12.
走，走，停
Okay, go, go, go, stop. Stop...
停下！我的天！
Rich, stop! That's... Jesus!
他們該死的村子 恰好坐落在
Their damn village happens to be resting on the richest unobtanium deposit
豐富的「鎢氪取」礦藏上 看看這寶貝！
within 200 klicks in any direction. I mean, look at all that cheddar!
- 誰來喊他們搬家 - 猜猜看
- Well, who gets them to move? - Guess.
- 假如他們不肯走？ - 看他們敢不敢
- What if they won't go? - I'm betting that they will.
好了，好了，聽著
Okay, okay, okay, okay, hey. Look. Look.
殺死原住民雖然影響不好
Killing the indigenous looks bad,
但比起傳媒 股東們更介意的是…
but there's one thing that shareholders hate more than bad press,
季度報表上的虧損 我無能為力
and that's a bad quarterly statement. I didn't make up the rules.
給我想個法子 騙他們遷移
So just find me a carrot that'll get them to move,
否則大家都不好過
otherwise it's gonna have to be all stick. Okay?
在挖土機到達之前 你還有三個月
You got three months. That's when the 'dozers get there.
你在浪費時間
Well, we're wasting time.
我喜歡這傢伙
I like this guy.
- 夥計們，現在… - 好吧，我們再過一遍
- Guys, right now... - Okay, let's run through them again.
莫阿特，神秘的女士
Mo'at. Dragon lady.
- 艾圖砍 - 艾圖看，他是部落酋長
- Eytucan. - Eytukan. He's the clan leader.
但莫阿特才是精神領袖 就像薩滿巫師
But she's the spiritual leader. Like a shaman.
明白
Got it.
- 豬泰 - 蘇泰
- T'su'tey. - Tsu'tey.
- 蘇泰 - 他將是下任酋長
- Tsu'tey. - He'll be the next clan leader.
- 娜塔瑞 - 她將是下任巫后
- Neytiri. - She'll be the next Tsahik.
他們將是夫妻領袖
They become a mated pair.
- 那誰是伊娃？ - 誰是伊娃？
- So who's this Eywa? - Who's Eywa?
他們唯一的女神 一切生靈的集合
Only their deity. Their goddess, made up of all living things.
是他們知道的一切
Everything they know!
哪怕學過一點點 都會知道這個
You'd know this if you had any training whatsoever.
不知誰約到了酋長女兒
Who's got a date with the chief's daughter?
- 算了吧，那是… - 好了，你兩個住嘴吧
- Come on. That's... - All right, knock it off, you two.
走吧，村莊開始很早
Let's go. Village life starts early.
別做特別的蠢事
Don't do anything unusually stupid.
放鬆，小子
Easy, boy.
帕蕾是母性
Pale is female.
好吧，放鬆，姑娘
Okay. Easy, girl.
這是「紮黑魯」，紐帶
That is tsaheylu. The bond.
感受她
Feel her.
感受她的心跳，她的呼吸
Feel her heartbeat. Her breath.
感受她強壯的腿
Feel her strong legs.
你可以告訴她幹什麼
You may tell her what to do.
裡面
Inside.
現在，說出方向
For now, say where to go.
前進！
Forward!
- 你該離開 - 不，你會想念我的
- You should go away. - No, you'd miss me.
你就知道你會英語
I knew you could speak English.
異族人一竅不通…
This alien will learn nothing...
…石頭都比他開竅…
...a rock sees more...
…看他那樣
...look at him.
再來
Again.
如果要進攻 情況會很複雜
If you want to hit this thing, it's gonna be complicated.
你的掃瞄看不到內部結構
Your scan doesn't show the internal structure.
外面有一圈石柱
There's an outer row of columns.
防守嚴密 這裡還有一圈
Real heavy duty. There's a secondary ring here,
還有內圈 有個塔形結構
and an inner ring. There's a core structure like a spiral.
用來上下移動
That's how they move up and down.
我們需要每個石柱 的詳細掃瞄
We're gonna need accurate scans on every column.
收到
Roger that.
關於結構 你還能提供什麼？
What else can you tell us about the structure?
我估計第二環 同時也是承重環
I'm guessing this secondary ring, that's also load-bearing.
- 我們去哪？ - 出去避避
- So where are we going? - Getting out of Dodge.
我不會讓帕克和邁爾斯為所欲為
I'm not about to let Selfridge and Quaritch micro-manage this thing.
在26區還有個移動鏈接點
There's a mobile link up at Site 26 we can work out of,
在高山上
way up in the mountains.
哈利路亞山？
The Hallelujah Mountains?
- 沒錯 - 說真的？
- That's right. - Are you serious?
- 是啊 - 好啊
- Yeah. - Yes!
潘朵拉傳說中的懸浮山 沒聽過？
The legendary floating mountains of Pandora. Heard of them?
我們接近了
We're getting close.
是啊，看我的儀表
Yeah, look at my instruments.
我們在亂流中
Yep. We're in the Flux Vortex.
現在開始要目飛了
We're VFR from here on.
什麼是目飛
What's VFR?
就是肉眼找到你的目的地
Means you gotta see where you're going.
- 但我什麼都看不到 - 對了，是不是有點刁
- You can't see anything. - Exactly. Ain't that a bitch?
我的天
Oh, my God.
看看你的表情
You should see your faces.
謝謝您乘坐潘朵拉航空
Thank you for flying Air Pandora.
歡迎到營地來
Welcome to camp.
- 這是我的舖位 - 這裡真亂
- So, this is my bunk. - This stuff is nasty.
- 諾曼，你在下面 - 好的
- Norm, go under. - All right.
- 格蕾絲都知道了 - 楚蒂，你用最上面的
- Grace didn't miss a thing. - Trudy, you'll take the top one.
他知道我和上校談話
She knew I was talking to the Colonel.
但是她需要 我的幫助回部落
But I had what she needed, a way back in with the clan,
所以她假裝好人
so she's playing nice.
傑克，向左拐 你的鏈接在最後
All right. Jake, hang a left. You'll be in the link at the end.
一號機，它是故障最少的
Unit one. Beulah. She's the least glitchy.
我的天！
Holy shit!
別盯她眼睛
Do not look in her eye.
伊卡蘭不是馬
Ikran is not horse.
一旦紐帶建立
Once tsaheylu is made,
伊卡蘭從一而終
ikran will fly with only one hunter in the whole life.
想要做獵人
To become taronyu, hunter,
你要挑你的伊卡蘭 它也必須選擇你
you must choose your own ikran and he must choose you.
- 什麼時候？ - 你準備好的時候
- When? - When you are ready.
好了，這是視頻日記12
Okay. This is video log 12.
時間是2132
Time's 2132.
必須得現在做嗎？ 我想要個架子
Do I have to do this now? I really need to get some rack.
不行 乘記憶還新鮮
No, now. When it's fresh.
好吧，地點：窩棚
Okay, location, shack,
日子開始混淆了
and the days are starting to blur together.
學語言真是痛苦，不過
The language is a pain, but, you know,
我發現就像拆卸武器 不斷重複再重複就好了
I figure it's like field-stripping a weapon. Just repetition, repetition.
更強些
Txur ni'ul. Stronger.
娜塔瑞叫我「死干木」，意思是白癡
Neytiri calls me skxawng. It means moron.
參與其中很重要
This is a very important part of it.
- 諾曼的態度也有改善 - 我見你，我見你
- Norm 's attitude has improved lately. - I see you. I see you.
但不僅僅是 「我見到你了」
But it's not just, "I'm seeing you in front of me,"
而是「我見到你本質，我見你」
it's "I see into you. I See you."
他回心轉意當然好 可他也認為我是「死干木」
It's good he's back on board, but he thinks I'm a skxawng, too.
"我接受你，我明白你" 所以你一定要搞懂它，好吧？
"I'm accepting you. I understand you." So you gotta get this, okay?
我要跑步了，來吧
I gotta run! Okay? Let's go.
我雙腳越來越強 每天跑的距離都在增加
My feet are getting tougher. I can run farther every day.
我必須相信身體的直覺
I have to trust my body to know what to do.
好啊，快看
Yeah! Check it out!
我靠
Oh, crap!
每一天都是追蹤水塘裡的線索
Every day it's reading the trails, the tracks at the waterhole,
都是些最微弱的氣味和聲音
the tiniest scents and sounds.
她一直在談 能量的流動，動物的靈魂
She's always going on about the flow of energy, the spirits of animals.
我真希望最後的考試 不是這個抱樹遊戲
I really hope this tree-hugger crap isn't on the final.
這不僅僅是手眼協調
This isn't just about eye-hand coordination out there, you know.
你需要聆聽她的話
You need to listen to what she says.
試著通過她的眼睛看森林
Try to see the forest through her eyes.
不好意思，這是我的日記
Excuse me. This is my video log here.
跟著娜塔瑞，不學快一點就完蛋了
With Neytiri, it's learn fast or die.
你開玩笑吧
You gotta be kidding me.
我和莫阿特談過 允許格蕾絲進入村莊
I talked Mo'at into letting Grace into the village.
看你們長多大了
Look how big you are.
從她學校關閉後 這是頭一次
It's the first time since her school was closed down.
你真漂亮
You are so pretty.
不行，給我回來
No, you don't. Come back here.
祝你胃口好
Bon app谷tit.
過來，大兵
Come on, Marine.
我想要去理解 這深層的聯繫
I'm trying to understand this deep connection
人們和森林的聯繫
the people have to the forest.
她談到一種能量網
She talks about a network of energy
一切活著生物的能量
that flows through all living things.
她說所有能量都是借來的
She says all energy is only borrowed,
有一天終需歸還
and one day you have to give it back.
我見你…
I see you...
…兄弟
...Brother
…也謝謝你
...and thank you.
你的靈魂跟隨伊娃
Your spirit goes with Eywa.
你的身體留在此處…
Your body stays behind...
…變成人們的一份子
...to become part of The People.
乾淨的手法
A clean kill.
你準備好了
You are ready.
學著駕馭它伊卡蘭，我們叫做班希斯
Learning to ride an ikran, we call them banshees,
是每個年輕獵人必過的測試
is the test every young hunter has to pass.
但這之前 你得去到班希斯的巢
But to do that, you gotta go where the banshees are.
現在呢？
Now what?
傑克先走
Jakesully will go first.
現在你挑選伊卡蘭 用你內心去感受
Now you choose your ikran. This you must feel inside.
如果它也選了你 像我一樣動作快點
If he also chooses you, move quick like I showed.
只有一次機會
You will have one chance, Jake.
怎麼知道它選了我？
How will I know if he chooses me?
他會想吃掉你
He will try to kill you.
多明顯
Outstanding.
我們跳舞吧
Let's dance.
這白癡死定了
That moron's going to die.
別害怕，戰士
Don't be afraid, warrior.
建紐帶
Make the bond!
不！
No!
傑克！
Jake!
紮黑魯，傑克
Tsaheylu, Jake.
紮黑魯！
Tsaheylu!
停下！
Stop!
這就對了，你是我的了
Yeah, that's right. You're mine. Huh?
初次飛行鞏固紐帶 不要等
First flight seals the bond. You cannot wait.
- 想著「飛」 - 飛？
- Think, "Fly!" - Fly?
該死的
God damn!
閉嘴，給我好好飛
Shut up and fly straight!
這就對了，左轉
That's it. Bank left!
平行，做得好
Level out! That's it.
傑克！
Jakesully!
嘿！
Hey!
我們走！
Let's go!
看，寶貝 我掌握了
Yeah, baby, I got this!
該死
Oh, shit!
騎馬我可能不在行 但這個我骨子裡就會！
I may not be much of a horse guy, but I was born to do this.
好啊
Yeah!
- 我這樣過來，你在這 - 對
- I came like this. This you. - Yeah, yeah.
- 我轉彎，感覺到風，轉得很強 - 我轉的很強烈
- I turn. I feel the wind. I turn very strong. - Look, yeah, see, I banked so hard...
靈魂之樹
The Tree of Souls.
他們最神聖的地方
It's their most sacred place.
看這裡顯示的離子亂流
See the Flux Vortex in these false color images?
對，就這影響我設備
Yeah, that's what messes up my instruments.
那裡的生物學現象太有趣了
There is something really interesting going on in there biologically.
我死都想去拿個樣本
I would die to get samples.
外來人是禁入的
Outsiders are strictly forbidden.
你這好運的豬
You lucky swine.
我是高高在上的冷血殺手
I was a stone-cold aerial hunter. Death from above.
問題是，不只你一個
Only problem is, you're not the only one.
下潛！
Dive!
衝，衝！
Go, go!
跟我來！
Follow me!
我們的人叫它：萊奧諾普暴龍獸
Our guys call it a Great Leonopteryx.
它是托盧克，最後之影
It is Toruk. Last Shadow.
當然了，死前最後看到就是它
Yeah, right. It's the last one you ever see.
我爺爺的爺爺是托盧克 馬克托
My grandfather's grandfather was Toruk Macto.
圖靈騎士
Rider of Last Shadow.
他騎這東西？
He rode this?
托盧克選擇了他
Toruk chose him.
從初歌之日起，只發生過5次
It has only happened five times since the time of the First Songs.
- 很長一段時間 - 是啊
- That's a long time. - Yes.
托盧克 馬克托代表力量
Toruk Macto was mighty.
在危機時刻，他把各部落團結一起
He brought the clans together in a time of great sorrow.
所有納美人知道這故事
All Na'vi people know the story.
一切都顛倒過來了 似乎那邊是真實世界
Everything is backwards now. Like out there is the true world
這邊才是個夢
and in here is the dream.
不敢相信 才經過了三個月
It's hard to believe it's only been three months.
我幾乎忘記了過去
I can barely remember my old life.
忘記了自己是誰
I don't know who I am anymore.
沒有在木頭裡迷失吧？
Haven't gotten lost in the woods, have you?
你上一份報告 都在兩周以前了
Your last report was more than two weeks ago.
我開始懷疑你的決心
I'm starting to doubt your resolve!
在我看來 是時候結束任務了
The way I see it, it's time to terminate the mission.
不，我還能幹
No, I can do this.
你已經做到了
You already have.
你給了我寶貴的內部資料
You give me good, usable intel.
還有靈魂之樹的地點
This Tree of Souls place.
當戰況不利時 我掌握了他們的命根子
Yeah, I got them by the balls with that when this turns into a shit fight,
現在該回來了
Now it's time to come in.
另外
By the way,
我幫你找回另一條腿
you gonna get your legs back.
對，我幫你徵得企業同意 已經定下了
Yeah. I got your corporate approval. It's a done deal.
今晚送你回去
Gonna have you on a shuttle tonight.
我是個講信用的
I'm a man of my word.
我得有始有終
I gotta finish this.
還差一件事
There's one more thing.
儀式！成人的最後一步
Ceremony. It's the final stage of becoming a man.
如果我完成了 就成為一份子了
If I do it, I'm one of them.
他們就會相信我
And they'll trust me.
然後就能勸他們搬家
And I can negotiate the terms of their relocation.
那你就快點做，下士
Well, then, you'd better get it done, Corporal.
納美人說 每個人都出生兩次
The Na 'vi say that every person is born twice.
第二次，是你贏得了人們中的地位
The second time is when you earn your place among The People forever.
你現在是奧馬地卡雅族的兒子了
You are now a son of the Omaticaya.
你是人們的一分子了
You are part of The People.
來，來
Come. Come.
這裡是我們祈禱之地
This is a place for prayers to be heard.
有時能聽到回應
And sometimes answered.
我們叫這些樹霧圖愛雅
We call these trees Utraya Mokri.
聲音之樹
The Tree of Voices.
先祖的聲音
The voices of our ancestors.
我能聽到他們
I can hear them.
他們活著，傑克
They live, Jake,
和伊娃一起
within Eywa.
你現在是奧馬地卡雅族了
You are Omaticaya now.
你可從家之樹取下材料 製成弓箭
You may make your bow from the wood of Hometree.
你還能選擇一個女人
And you may choose a woman.
你可選許多好女人
We have many fine women.
泥納是最好的歌手
Ninat is the best singer.
但我不想要泥納
But I don't want Ninat.
培拉是個好獵手
Peyral is a good hunter.
是啊，她真是好獵手
Yeah, she is a good hunter.
但我已經選好
I've already chosen.
可這女孩也必須選擇我
But this woman must also choose me.
她也已經選好
She already has.
我和你在一起了，傑克
I am with you now, Jake.
我們是終身伴侶
We are mated for life.
你到底在幹什麼，傑克？
What the hell are you doing, Jake?
傑克！
Jake!
別忘了相位整合
Don't forget your phase integration.
- 傑克！ - 不，不，中間的按鈕
- Jake! - No, no, the middle button.
- 你得吃點東西 - 對，就這個
- You gotta eat something. - Yeah, there you go.
傑克！傑克，醒醒！傑克，求你了！
Jake! Jake. Wake up! Jake, please!
別逼我強迫瘸子吃飯
Don't make me force-feed a cripple.
格蕾絲，我不想…嘿！
Grace, I don't want... Hey!
傑克！
Jake!
好吧
Okay.
給你，我吃完了，我們開始吧
Here. I'm done. Let's go.
你上次洗澡是什麼時候？
And when was the last time you took a shower?
- 我不需要洗澡 - 天哪，大兵
- I don't need a shower. - Jesus, Marine.
傑克！
Jake!
傑克！醒醒！傑克！醒醒！
Jake! Wake up! Jake! Wake up!
嘿！
Hey!
停下！停下！
Stop! Stop!
- 傑克！ - 退回去，停下！
- Jake! - Go back, stop!
嘿，老板
Hey, boss.
嘿！
Hey!
- 怎麼了？ - 有個土著人
- What? - I got a native
像小雞一樣跳來跳去，他攔著我的刀了
doing the funky chicken here. He's blocking my blade.
繼續前進，他會跑開的
Well, keep going. He'll move.
這些人必須了解我們是不會停的 快點，前進，前進，前進
These people have to learn that we don't stop. Come on, go, go, go.
停下！嘿！
Stop! Hey!
快跑！快跑！
Go! Go!
看到沒？他跑開了
There, see? He moved.
哥們，哥們，哇，哥們！哥們！不！
Dude, dude. Whoa, dude! Dude, no!
我看不到了！
I'm blind.
- 傑克！ - 娜塔瑞！
- Jake! - Neytiri!
來，快跑！
Here, come on!
在這裡暫停
Freeze it right there.
拉近鏡頭，強化
Scale up. Enhance.
狗娘養的
Son of a bitch.
難以置信
Unbelievable.
- 給我找個飛行員 - 是，先生
- Get me a pilot. - Yes, sir.
蘇泰將領導戰爭
Tsu'tey will lead the war party.
請停一下！
Stop please!
這只會讓情況變得更糟
This will only make it worse.
你別在這裡發表言論！
You do not speak here!
我們要直搗他們的心臟
We will strike them in the heart.
蘇泰！不要這麼做
Tsu'tey! Don't do this.
- 你！ - 聽著，兄弟…
- You! - Listen. Brother...
- 你和這個女人配對了？ - 噢，完蛋了
- You mated with this woman? - Oh, shit.
是真的嗎？
Is this true?
我們在伊娃面前結合，是既成事實
We are mated before Eywa. It is done.
兄弟，請你
Brother, please.
不要攻擊天空人，如果你攻擊他們的話 奧馬地卡雅部落會死很多人
Do not attack the Sky People. Many Omaticaya will die if you do.
你不是我的兄弟！
You are not my brother!
我不是你的敵人！
And I am not your enemy!
敵人在那里，他們非常強大！
The enemy is out there, and they are very powerful!
衝！衝！衝！
Go! Go! Go!
- 我能跟他們交涉 - 不要再交涉了
- I can talk to them. - No more talk.
蘇泰！
Tsu'tey!
我是奧馬地卡雅人，跟你們是一起的
I am Omaticaya. I am one of you.
我有發表言論的權利
And I have the right to speak.
我有話要對
I have something to say...
你們所有人說
...to all of you.
這些話猶如巨石壓在我的心頭
The words are like stones in my heart.
長官，對不起，不，不，不！停下！
Sir, I'm sorry. No, no, no! Hold on!
你們不能打攪正在進行的連接進程！
You can't interrupt a link in progress!
這非常危險！
It's very dangerous!
格蕾絲！
Grace!
噢，不
Oh, no.
- 等等！ - 別站起來，先生
- Wait! - Stay down, sir.
好了，聽著…
Okay. Look...
我被派到這裡來…
I was sent here to...
你們看到了嗎？
You see?
它是藏在這個軀殼裡的惡魔
It is a demon in a false body.
- 你瘋了嗎？ - 你越界了
- Are you out of your goddamn mind? - You crossed the line.
把這家伙帶走
Wheel this meat out of here.
傑克！這裡到底怎麼回事？
Jake! What the hell is going on here?
你讓我失望了，孩子
You let me down, son.
那麼，是怎樣
So, what,
你給自己找了根土著尾巴
you find yourself some local tail
然後就徹底忘了自己的組織？
and you just completely forget what team you're playing for?
帕克，還有時間來挽回現在的形勢
Parker, there is time to salvage the situation.
- 帕克… - 閉上你的臭嘴！
- Parker... - Shut your pie hole!
不然怎樣，瑞克大兵？你要槍斃我嗎？
Or what, Ranger Rick? You gonna shoot me?
- 我可以那麼做 - 你得給你的狗戴上口套
- I could do that. - You need to muzzle your dog.
我們可以冷靜一點嗎？
Yeah, can we just take this down a couple of notches, please?
你說你想讓你的人活著？
You say you want to keep your people alive?
那麼你就該開始聽她的話
You start by listening to her.
那些樹對奧馬地卡雅部落來說很神聖
Those trees were sacred to the Omaticaya
- 超乎你想象的神聖 - 你知道嗎？
- in a way you can't imagine. - You know what?
再這裡隨便扔一根棍子
You throw a stick in the air around here,
都會落在某種神聖的植物上
it's gonna land on some sacred fern,
- 看在上帝的份上！ - 我說的不是
- for Christ's sake! - I'm not talking
某種異教的巫術，我說的是真實存在
about some kind of pagan voodoo here. I'm talking about something real,
在這森林裡可以衡量的東西
something measurable in the biology of the forest.
到底是什麼？
Which is what, exactly?
我們知道的是
What we think we know
這些樹的樹根之間存在某種
is that there is some kind of electrochemical communication
電氣化的通訊，就像神經元的神經鍵一樣
between the roots of the trees, like the synapses between neurons.
每棵樹與周圍的樹的連接 達到10的四次方個
And each tree has ten-to-the-fourth connections to the trees around it.
潘朵拉星球上的樹有10的12次方棵
And there are ten-to-the-twelfth trees on Pandora.
我猜，這數量很大
Which is a lot, I'm guessing.
比人類大腦的連接還要多
It's more connections than the human brain.
懂了嗎？這是個網絡
Get it? It's a network.
是個全星球的網絡，納美人可以登錄上去
It's a global network, and the Na'vi can access it.
他們可以上傳和下載數據，記憶
They can upload and download data. Memories.
就在你們剛毀掉的那些地點
At sites like the one you just destroyed.
對！
Yes!
你們這些人到底吸了什麼毒品了？
What the hell have you people been smoking out there?
他們不過是些該死的樹！
They're just goddamn trees!
- 你得醒醒了，帕克 - 不，你需要醒醒
- You need to wake up, Parker. - No. You need to wake up.
這個世界的財富不在地里 而是在我們周圍
The wealth of this world isn't in the ground. It's all around us.
納美人知道這個 所以他們在抗爭著保護它
The Na'vi know that, and they are fighting to defend it.
如果你想跟他們分享這個世界 你得理解他們
If you want to share this world with them, you need to understand them.
我說我們很了解他們，這得感謝傑克
I'd say we understand them just fine, thanks to Jake here.
嘿，博士，過來看一眼
Hey, Doc, come take a look.
他們不會放棄他們的家園
They're not gonna give up their home.
他們不會達成協議
They're not gonna make a deal.
為的是什麼？低度啤酒嗎？
For what? Lite beer?
藍色牛仔褲嗎？
And blue jeans?
我們有的東西，他們都不需要
There's nothing that we have that they want.
他們讓我出來做的所有事 都是在浪費時間
Everything they sent me out here to do is a waste of time.
他們不會離開家園之樹
They're never gonna leave Hometree.
既然不能達成協議，我想事情就很簡單了
So, since a deal can't be made, I guess things get real simple.
傑克，謝謝，我好感動啊
Jake, thanks. I'm getting all emotional.
我都想跟你來個大濕吻
I might just give you a big wet kiss.
做這事時，我會將土著人傷亡降到最低
I'll do it with minimal casualties to the indigenous.
我先會用毒氣驅趕他們
I'll drive them out with gas first.
會很人道的
It'll be humane.
差不多吧
More or less.
好吧，我們開始行動
All right, let's pull the trigger.
- 大家快點 - 噢，天哪
- Come on, people. - Oh, man.
打好包，準備出發
Let's pack it up, let's go.
就這樣了
This is how it's done.
你想要別人腳下的土地時
When people are sitting on shit that you want,
你把他們變成你的敵人 然後你就能正義地去奪取
you make them your enemy. Then you're justified in taking it.
邁爾斯發動武裝直升機了 他要攻擊家園之樹了
Quaritch is rolling the gunships. He's gonna hit Hometree.
我的天啊
My God.
- 邁爾斯博士！你不能上這裡來！ - 給我走開！
- Dr. Augustine! You cannot be up here! - Back off!
帕克，等一下，別打了 你要攻打的這些人…
Parker. Wait. Stop. These are people you're about to...
- 不，不，不，不，不 - 我說走開！
- No. No, no, no, no. - I said back off!
他們是生活在樹上的招蒼蠅的野人！
They're fly-bitten savages that live in a tree!
好嗎？看看周圍吧！
All right? Look around!
我不知道你看到沒有，可我看到很多樹！ 他們可以搬家！
I don't know about you, but I see a lot of trees! They can move!
- 你們可不可以… - 是，長官
- Can you guys just please... - Yes, sir.
那裡有家庭，有小孩，嬰兒
There are families in there. There are children. Babies.
你要殺害孩子嗎？
Are you gonna kill children?
你不想讓你的雙手沾上那種鮮血，相信我
You don't want that kind of blood on your hands. Believe me.
讓我試著去說服他們吧
Just let me try to talk them out.
他們信任我
They trust me.
趕緊校准，我們要進去了，馬上
Calibrate fast. We're going in, right now.
校准三和四
Calibrating three and four.
- 開始運行 - 啟動，三十秒
- Run sequence. - Initiating. Thirty seconds.
聽著，給你一個小時
Listen to me. You've got one hour.
不然你女朋友還在裡頭的時候 斧頭就會落下來
Unless you want your girlfriend in there when the ax comes down,
你讓他們撤離，一個小時
you get them to evacuate. One hour.
父親！
Father!
母親！
Mother!
艾圖看，我有話要說
Eytukan, I have something to say.
聽他說！
Listen!
說吧，傑克
Speak, Jakesully.
有惡魔要降臨了
A great evil is upon us...
天空人來了
The Sky People are coming...
他們要毀掉家園之樹
...to destroy Hometree.
跟他們說他們很快就要來了
Look, tell them they're gonna be here soon.
你們必須離開，不然會死的
You have to leave, or you're gonna die.
你確定嗎？
Are you certain of this?
他們派我來學習你們的生活方式
Look, they sent me here to learn your ways
有一天我就可以給你們傳遞信息 這樣你們才會相信
so one day I could bring this message and that you would believe it.
傑克，你什麼意思？你知道這事會發生？
What are you saying, Jake? You knew this would happen?
對
Yes.
一開始，我只是聽從命令
Look, at first it was just orders,
可後來事情改變了
and then everything changed.
好嗎？我墜入了情網
Okay? I fell in love.
我愛上了森林，我愛上了奧馬地卡雅人
I fell in love with the forest and with the Omaticaya people.
也愛上了你
And with you.
- 我以前那麼信任你 - 愛上你了，愛上你了
- I trusted you. - With you. With you.
- 我以前那麼信任你！ - 請現在也請信任我
- I trusted you! - Trust me now, please.
你永遠都不會是我們的一員
You will never be one of The People!
- 我不應該… - 我們盡力想制止他們的！
- I shouldn't have... - We tried to stop them!
娜塔瑞，求妳了！求妳了
Neytiri, please! Please.
把他們綁起來
Bind them.
現在就走！
Leave now!
你們必須得走了，他們要來了
You have to go. They're coming!
預定攻擊目標時間，行動
Time on target, one mike.
收到，我們看到了
Copy. We have a visual.
收到，繼續向030進發
Roger that. Stay on heading 030.
收到，030
Roger, 030.
- 跑進森林里！ - 他們來了！
- Run to the forest! - They're coming!
- 他們會毀了整個地方 - 娜塔瑞，妳現在必須離開！
- They will destroy this place. - Neytiri, you must go now!
跑進森林裡！快跑！
Run to the forest! Run!
快跑！快跑！
Run! Run!
不要害怕
Have no fear.
不！該死的，快跑！
No! God damn it, run!
騎上飛龍…
Take the ikran...
…從上面攻擊
...attack from above.
這真是棵該死的大樹
That is one big damn tree.
瞧，瞧，瞧，我得說外交失敗了
Well, well, well. I'd say diplomacy has failed.
好了，大家，我們把這事了結吧
All right, people, let's get this done!
我要每個毒氣彈都攻入前門
I want every gas round you got right in the front door.
收到，40號彈發射
Roger. CS.40's going hot.
- 發射 - 發射了
- Fire. - Firing.
中，幹得好，優秀
Bingo. Mighty good shooting, ace.
長官，他們回擊了
Sir, they've opened fire.
你在跟我開玩笑呢吧！
You've got to be kidding me!
這些愚蠢的雜種不懂我們的意思
These dumb bastards ain't getting the message.
好吧，我們來升級戰火吧
All right, let's turn up the heat.
- 換燃燒彈！ - 換燃燒彈
- Switch incendiaries! - Switching incendiaries.
發射
Fire.
不！
No!
大家都去森林裡
Get everyone to the forest.
驅散蟑螂就是用這個方法
And that's how you scatter the roaches.
娜塔瑞！
Neytiri!
我們得離開！他要炸這裡了！
We gotta move! He's gonna blow the columns!
我的天啊！
My God!
- 莫阿特！不要！ - 如果你是我們的一份子
- Mo'at! No! - Lf you are one of us,
幫助我們
help us.
全體都有，換導彈
All call signs, switch missiles.
給我換上強烈炸藥，轟炸西邊的樹根
Give me HE's at the base of the west columns.
這邊！
This way!
換導彈
Rider section, switch missiles.
一、二
- One's good. - Two's rocks up.
- 三 - 好，寶貝，來點吧！
- Three's up. - Yeah, baby, get some!
查理﹒奧斯卡，軍火犯準備好了
Charlie Oscar, Gunrunner standing by.
- 發射吧 - 批准發射
- Bring it down. - Cleared hot.
快，格蕾絲，快跑！
Come on, Grace, move!
趴下，趴下！
Down! Head down!
快，快，趴下！
Come on, come on! Down!
- 打中了 - 正中目標
- Solid hits. - Solid rocks on target.
他娘的
Screw this.
嘿，你他媽的在幹嘛？
Hey! What the hell are you doing?
我當兵不為這個！
I didn't sign up for this shit!
重復，連續發射
Repeat. Ripple fire.
快跑！快跑！快跑！
Go! Go! Go!
不，不，退後！退後！
No, no, get back! Back!
快點！快點，快跑！快跑！
Come on! Come on, move! Move!
大家干幹得好，今晚第一輪我請客
That's good work, people. First round's on me tonight.
我們去跳布吉舞
Let's boogie.
龍向左，打道回府
Dragon coming left, heading home.
軍火犯向左，打道回府
Gunrunner coming left.
- 雷聲收到 - 駕駛者收到
- Thunder copies. - Rider section copies.
父親！
Father!
女兒…
Daughter...
拿著…我的…弓
take... my... bow.
保護部落的人
Protect The People.
娜塔瑞！
Neytiri!
- 對不起，對不起 - 走開
- I'm sorry. I'm sorry. - Get away.
走開！
Get away!
離開這裡！
Get away from here!
別再回來！
Never come back!
把插頭拔了
Pull the plug.
- 不，你不可以這麼做 - 你不能這麼做！
- No, you can't do that! - You can't do that!
- 冷靜！冷靜！ - 不！求你了！
- Calm down! Calm down! - No! Please!
我是夢想能帶來和平的戰士
I was a warrior who dreamed he could bring peace.
可是遲早，都會從夢中醒來
Sooner or later, though, you always have to wake up.
走吧！
Let's go!
放下他！
Put him down!
你這個殺人犯！
You murderer!
兄弟怎麼樣？很久不見了
What's going on, brother? Long time no see.
嘿
Hey.
我個人認為這些叛徒們不應該有牛排吃
Personally, I don't feel these tree-hugging traitors deserve steak.
他們還有牛排吃？真是狗屁，讓我看看
They get steak? That's bullshit. Let me see that.
對，你知道這是什麼，趴下
Yeah. You know what that is. Down.
- 楚蒂！ - 趴下去
- Trudy! - All the way down.
麥克斯！
Max!
楚蒂，去開直升機！快！
Trudy, fire up the ship! Go!
給你
Here.
- 安全，快點 - 給你
- Clear. Come on. - Here you go.
麥克斯，留在這裡 我需要有我信任的人留在內部
Max, stay here. I need someone on the inside I can trust.
好的，走
Okay. Go.
安全
Clear.
來吧，寶貝
Come on, baby.
上校？長官？我這裡有情況
Colonel? Sir? I got a situation here.
薩姆森1-6，未經授權發動飛機
It's Samson 1-6. Unauthorized engine start.
三！
Three!
快！
Come on!
戴上面罩！
Mask on!
氧氣，氧氣，氧氣！
Gas, gas, gas!
我被射擊了，快點吧！
I'm taking fire! Let's go!
抓著我的手，我們上來了，走吧！
Grab my hand! Come on, we're in. Let's go!
快點，走吧，走吧，走！
Come on, let's go! Let's go, go!
上校！
Colonel!
- 好！好！ - 好了！對！
- Yeah! Yeah! - All right! Yes!
- 完蛋 - 大家都沒事吧？
- Crap. - Everybody all right back there?
噢，對，寶貝！
Oh, yeah, baby!
- 諾曼，你還好嗎？ - 對！
- Norm, you good? - Yeah!
這要毀我一整天了
This is gonna ruin my whole day.
- 格蕾絲中彈了！ - 什麼？
- Grace is hit! - What?
- 把急救箱拿過來 - 急救箱！
- Get the trauma kit. - Trauma kit!
- 繼續壓著，格蕾絲 - 急救箱在前面，在艙壁
- Keep the pressure on, Grace. - Trauma kit's forward, on the bulkhead.
- 堅持住，格蕾絲 - 不要緊，沒關系的
- Hang on, Grace. - Doesn't matter. It's fine.
- 可以了 - 升起來
- You're good to go. - Take it up!
等一下，我在拉
Hold on. I'm pulling pitch.
安全！
You're clear!
一直往北飛，帶我們去到深山裡
Just keep going north. Get us deep in the mountains.
收到
Copy that.
- 諾曼，你那裡都好嗎？ - 對！還在這裡
- Norm, you all good up there? - Yep! Still here.
至少，他們追查不到我們的行蹤了 在漩渦深處是偵查不到的
Well, at least they can't track us up here. Not this far into the Vortex.
在靈魂之樹這裡是漩渦最強的，對吧？
It's strongest at the Tree of Souls, right?
對
Yeah.
很好，因為我們就是去那裡
Good. 'Cause that's where we're going.
哦，疼
Ouch.
你這個大孩子
You big baby.
我們去哪裡？
We're moving.
我會找人幫你，格蕾絲
I'm gonna get you some help, Grace.
我是個科學家，記得嗎？
I'm a scientist, remember?
我不相信童話
I don't believe in fairy tales.
納美人能幫助你
The People can help you.
我知道的
I know it.
他們為什麼幫我們？
Why would they help us?
納美人說伊娃會應驗的
The People say Eywa will provide.
沒有家，沒有希望
With no home, no hope,
只有一個地方可以去
there was only one place they could go.
連接啟動了
Link's running.
- 我們的計劃是什麼，傑克？ - 沒有計劃
- What's the plan here, Jake? - There's no plan.
蘇泰現在成為部落領袖了 他不會讓你靠近那個地方的
Tsu'tey is Olo'eyktan now. He's not gonna let you near that place.
我準備試試看
I gotta try.
啟動
Launching.
被驅逐者
Outcast.
叛徒
Betrayer.
異己
Alien.
我在這個地方無立足之地
I was in the place the eye does not see.
我需要他們的幫助，他們需要我的幫助
I needed their help, and they needed mine.
可想要再次面對他們
But to ever face them again,
我需要把自己提高到新的層次
I was gonna have to take it to a whole new level.
有時候一個瘋狂的舉動能扭轉乾坤
Sometimes your whole life boils down to one insane move.
我們得做一些事
There's something we gotta do.
你不會喜歡的事
You're not gonna like it.
我是這樣想的，圖靈鳥在天上所向披靡
The way I had it figured, Toruk is the baddest cat in the sky.
從來沒有被攻擊過
Nothing attacks him.
慢慢的，孩子
Easy, boy.
那麼他為什麼還要往上看呢？
So why would he ever look up?
當然，這只是一個想法
But that was just a theory.
圖靈鳥騎士？
Toruk Macto?
我看到你了
I See you.
我很恐懼，傑克
I was afraid, Jake.
為我的人民而恐懼
For my people.
現在我不恐懼了
I'm not anymore.
蘇泰，埃特尤之子
Tsu'tey, son of Ateyo...
我站在你的面前
...I stand before you...
準備為奧馬地卡雅人民效力
...ready to serve the Omaticaya people.
你是領袖，你是偉大的戰士
You are Olo'eyktan, and you are a great warrior.
沒有你，我無法成事
I can't do this without you.
圖靈騎士
Toruk Macto,
我要和你一起飛翔
I will fly with you.
我的朋友要死了
My friend is dying.
格蕾絲要死了
Grace is dying.
我祈求伊娃的幫助
I beg the help of Eywa.
看看我們在哪裡，格蕾絲
Look where we are, Grace.
我得取一些標本
I need to take some samples.
聖母將選擇拯救
The Great Mother may choose to save all that she is
這具軀體
in this body.
這有可能嗎？
Is that possible?
她必須經過伊娃的治療，然後回來
She must pass through the eye of Eywa and return.
可，傑克
But, Jakesully,
她非常虛弱
she is very weak.
堅持住，格蕾絲，他們會治好你的
Hang on, Grace. They're gonna fix you up.
請傾聽我們，聖母
Hear us please, All Mother.
伊娃，救她吧
Eywa, help her.
把這個靈魂帶走
Take this spirit into you...
救活她，讓她回到我們的身邊
...and breathe her back to us.
讓她跟我們一起行走
Let her walk among us...
作為納美人的一份子
...as one of The People.
傑克
Jake.
格蕾絲
Grace.
我和她在一起，杰克
I'm with her, Jake.
她是真的！
She's real!
格蕾絲？格蕾絲，格蕾絲！
Grace? Grace, please. Grace!
怎麼了？
What's happening?
格蕾絲！
Grace!
怎麼了？
What's happening?
起作用了嗎？
Did it work?
她傷得太嚴重了，時間來不及了
Her wounds were too great. It was not enough time.
她現在跟伊娃在一起了
She is with Eywa now.
請允許我說話
With your permission, I will speak now.
希望能榮幸地請你幫我做翻譯
You would honor me by translating.
天空人給我們一個信息
The Sky People have sent us a message
他們能拿走他們想要的一切
that they can take whatever they want
沒人可以阻止他們
and no one can stop them.
我們要帶給他們一個信息
Well, we will send them a message.
風有多快，你們就能飛多快
You ride out as fast as the wind can carry you.
你讓其他部族的人來
You tell the other clans to come.
你告訴他們圖靈騎士向他們發出邀請
You tell them Toruk Macto calls to them.
現在你們跟著我一起飛！
And you fly now with me!
我的兄弟們！姐妹們！
My brothers! Sisters!
我們要給天空人看看
And we will show the Sky People
他們不能拿走他們想要的一切
that they cannot take whatever they want,
這裡
and that this,
這裡是我們的土地！
this is our land!
呀！
Yah!
我們去到四風
We rode out to the four winds.
去到平原馬上部族
To the horse clans of the plain.
回到星球上去！
Back to the stars!
去到東海的伊克蘭部落
To the ikran people of the Eastern Sea.
為了我們孩子的孩子
For our children's children!
當圖靈騎士號召時，他們一呼百應
When Toruk Macto called them, they came.
呀！
Yah!
基地裡的所有人，你們所有人
Everyone on this base, every one of you,
都在為生存而戰
is fighting for survival.
這是事實！
That's a fact!
外面的土著部落正集結準備攻擊我們
There's an aboriginal horde out there massing for an attack.
現在，這些軌道圖像告訴我
Now, these orbital images tell me
敵人的數量在一天之內
that the hostiles' numbers have gone from a few hundred
從幾百變成了兩千多
to well over 2,000 in one day.
人數還在增多
And more are pouring in.
一周內，將會有兩萬人
In a week's time, there could be 20,000 of them.
這樣的話，他們將會突破我們的防線
At that point, they will overrun our perimeter.
這是不會發生的！
Well, that's not gonna happen!
只有先發制人的進攻才能確保我們的安全
Our only security lies in pre-emptive attack.
我們將以暴制暴
We will fight terror with terror.
現在敵人們相信他們的高山大本營
Now, the hostiles believe that this mountain stronghold of theirs
是受到保護的
is protected by their...
受到他們的女神的保護
Their deity.
我們摧毀他們的大本營
And when we destroy it,
會給他們的種族記憶帶來嚴重的打擊
we will blast a crater in their racial memory so deep
他們再也不敢靠近這方圓1000公里的地方
that they won't come within 1,000 klicks of this place ever again.
而這個，也是個事實
And that, too, is a fact.
好！好
Yeah! Yeah.
傑克，這裡已經瘋了，全體總動員 他們把飛船裝備成轟炸機了
Jake, it's crazy here. It's full mobilization. They're rigging the shuttle as a bomber.
他們裝備了巨型的礦山炸藥
They've got these huge pallets of mine explosives.
用於某種震懾行動
It's for some kind of shock-and-awe campaign.
全是該死的大殺傷性炸彈
Fricking daisy cutters!
邁爾斯已經全面接手，主持大局 無可阻擋
Quaritch has taken over. He's rolling, and there's no stopping him.
- 什麼時候？ - 明早六點
- When? - 0600 tomorrow.
- 麥克斯！麥克斯！ - 我得走了
- Max! Max! - I gotta go.
我們完蛋了
We're screwed!
我還希望能有一些不包括殉難在內的
And I was hoping for some sort of tactical plan
戰略計劃
that didn't involve martyrdom.
我們要用弓箭對付武裝直升飛機
We're going up against gunships with bows and arrows.
我在外面有15個部落種族的人
I have 15 clans out there.
有2000多個戰士
That's over 2,000 warriors.
現在，我們了解這些山 我們能飛過去，你能飛過去，他們不能
Now, we know these mountains. We fly them. You fly them. They don't.
他們的設備在這里行不通 導彈追蹤沒有用
Their instruments won't work up here. Missile tracking won't work.
他們得有視野才能開火
They'll have to fire a line of sight.
如果他們挑起戰爭 那麼我們就有主場優勢
If they bring the fight to us, then we have the home-field advantage.
你知道他會直接把炸彈投到靈魂之樹
You know he's gonna commit that bomber straight to the Tree of Souls.
對，我知道
Yeah, I know.
如果他們炸掉靈魂之樹，就完了
If they get to the Tree of Souls, it's over.
那可是他們與祖先伊娃的直接聯系
That's their direct line to Eywa, their ancestors.
這會摧毀他們的
It'll destroy them.
那我想我們最好阻止他
Then I guess we'd better stop him.
現在我可能只是對著一棵樹說話
I'm probably just talking to a tree right now.
可如果你在那裡，我要給你提個醒
But if you're there, I need to give you a heads-up.
如果格蕾絲跟你在一起，搜尋她的記憶
If Grace is with you, look into her memories.
看看我們來自的世界
See the world we come from.
那裡沒有綠色
There's no green there.
他們殺了他們的母親
They killed their Mother.
在這裡他們也會做同樣的事
And they're gonna do the same here.
更多的天空人會到來
More Sky People are gonna come.
就像永遠下不完的雨一樣，一直都有人來
They're gonna come like a rain that never ends.
除非我們阻止他們
Unless we stop them.
你選擇了我
Look, you chose me for something.
我會挺身而出，參加戰鬥
I will stand and fight.
你知道我會的
You know I will.
可是我需要一點幫助
But I need a little help here.
我們的聖母不會幫助任何一邊，傑克
Our Great Mother does not take sides, Jake.
她只保護生命的平衡
She protects only the balance of life.
這值得一試
It was worth a try.
對！對！就是這樣！
Yeah! Yeah! That's what I'm talking about!
Yeah! Yeah! That's what I'm talking about, man!
我是小組領導，我們在進入漩渦
This is Group Leader. We are entering the Flux Vortex.
- 轉到人工駕駛模式 - 收到，人工駕駛模式
- Switch to manual flight mode. - Copy. Manual flight mode.
我是龍爸爸
This is Papa Dragon.
我想讓這個任務速戰速決 我想回家吃晚飯
I want this mission high and tight. I want to be home for dinner.
- 重裝小組，出發 - 好了，女士們，給他們點苦果嘗嘗吧
- Suit Team, go. - All right, ladies, let's bring the pain!
快，快，快！
Move, move, move!
喝彩1-1，向左走
Bravo 1-1, move left.
喝彩1-1，向左走，注意側面
Bravo 1-1 moving left. Watch flank.
- 注意隊形，繼續前進 - 收到
- Watch formation. Keep moving. - Roger that.
查理2-1，注意保持距離
Charlie 2-1, watch your spacing.
收到，完畢
Copy that. Over.
向上看，查看上方，注意看熱能掃描
Eyes up. Check that overhead. And watch those thermal scans.
全體都有，爸爸帶頭，向目標前進
All call signs, Papa has lead, pushing to target.
護航機，跟緊我的飛船
Escorts, stay close on my shuttle.
太近了，漆都快被刮掉了
We are gonna lose some paint in here.
槍手們，注意眼觀八方
Gun crews, keep your head on a swivel.
不要犯錯，我們就在那裡
Make no mistake, people, they're out there.
好了，目標近在眼前，前方四公里
All right, people, target in sight. Range, four klicks.
瓦爾基莉1-6，準備彈藥
Valkyrie 1-6, get your payload ready.
- 收到，準備投放炸藥 - 上士，準備武器
- Copy. Prepare to offload. - Staff Sergeant, stage the weapon.
推過去！來吧！
Roll it to the ramp! Let's go!
停！
Hold!
查理2-1，顯示大規模敵軍活動
Charlie 2-1, got big movement.
- 大家別動 - 停下，停下
- Hold position. - Hold up, hold up.
- 這裡顯示500米外有人活動 - 查理2-1，別動
- We got movement out there, 500 meters. - Charlie 2-1, hold position.
長官，顯示地面有活動！非常快
Sir, ground has movement! Fast approaching.
-查理﹒奧斯卡，駕駛者 - 準備發射
- Charlie Oscar, Rider section. - Firing line!
目標靠近，前面400米
Targets closing. Range, 400 meters.
- 這個不能清除嗎？ - 長官，不能，這裡是旋渦
- Can't you clean it up? - No, sir. It's the Flux.
兄弟，我要去殺條路出來，你在後面跟著
Brother, I'm gonna punch a hole. You follow me through.
所有飛機，馬上開火！馬上開火！
All aircraft, weapons free! Weapons free!
往右邊，轉過來
Break right. Come around.
開槍射擊！
Light them up!
放棄隊形，追擊所有敵人
Break formation, engage all hostiles.
對！給你點顏色看看
Yeah! Get some!
天蠍隊，追蹤攻擊
Scorpions, pursue and destroy.
傑克！傑克！聽到沒？
Jake! Jake! You copy?
我們落後了！我們被襲擊了！
We're falling back! We're getting hammered!
收到，離開那裡
Copy. Get out of there.
那是他，給我追！
That's him. Get after him!
把他幹掉！
Take him out!
攻擊她！
Light her up!
就那裡
Right there!
不是只有你有槍，賤人
You're not the only one with a gun, bitch.
- 別讓她跑了 - 跟著她
- Keep her in your sights. - Purging. Feeding the leak.
子彈上膛
Arming all pods.
就是這樣！
That's it!
塞澤！
Seze!
羅格一中彈，我進去了
Rogue One is hit. I'm going in.
對不起，傑克
Sorry, Jake.
發射
Fire.
蘇泰！兄弟，你能聽到嗎？
Tsu'tey! Brother, do you read?
羅格一，能聽到嗎？
Rogue One, you copy?
楚蒂！
Trudy!
距離目標時間，兩分鐘
Time to target, two minutes.
瓦爾基莉1-6，批准發射
Valkyrie 1-6, you are cleared and hot.
收到，龍，開始炸彈轟炸
Copy, Dragon. We are starting our bomb run.
- 激發一號炸彈！ - 一號炸彈激發了！
- Arm number one! - Number one armed!
傑克！
Ma Jake!
收到
I read you.
- 娜塔瑞 - 塞澤死了
- Neytiri! - Seze's dead.
他們很近了，很多人
They are very close. They are many.
不要攻擊
Do not attack.
你聽到沒有，娜塔瑞？
Do you read me, Neytiri?
不要攻擊！
Do not attack!
現在撤退，離開那裡，這是命令！
Fall back now. Get out of there! That's an order!
娜塔瑞
Neytiri!
顯示有活動，顯示有活動
I got movement, I got movement.
停下別動，有東西過來了
Hold position. Something's coming.
喝彩1-1，我這裡有情況 把屏幕轉過來
Bravo 1-1, I got a big seating. Turn screens over.
- 200米處有活動 - 保持隊形
- We got movement 200 meters. - Hold your formation.
- 全面戒備 注意側面
- Be ready. - Watch your flanks.
一百米，迅速移近
Hundred meters and closing fast.
我們得離開這裡！
We gotta get out of here!
- 撤退！撤退！ - 快，快，快
- Fall back! Fall back! - Move! Move! Move!
撤退！撤退！撤退！
Fall back! On the run! On the run!
傑克，伊娃聽到你說的話了
Jake, Eywa has heard you.
伊娃聽到了
Eywa has heard you!
衝啊！
Come on!
撤退！快！快！
Fall back! Move! Move!
長官！所有護航機都墜毀了或掉隊了
Sir! All escorts are down or falling back.
我們來解決這事，瓦爾基莉1-6，我是龍
Let's get this done. Valkyrie 1-6, this is Dragon.
- 準備射擊目標 - 收到，準備射擊目標
- Press to target. - Copy. Pressing to target.
距離發射，30秒
Stand by to drop, 30 seconds.
聽我口令，2，1，投放
On my mark. Two, one, mark.
投放！投放！投放！快，快，快，快！
Drop! Drop! Drop! Go, go, go, go!
天哪！
Brace!
是傑克
It's Sully.
- 戴上面罩！ - 船艙破裂！
- Mask on! - Breach alarm!
來吧，來爸爸這裡
Come on. Come to papa.
放手吧，邁爾斯！
Give it up, Quaritch!
一切都結束了
It's all over.
只要我還呼吸，就都還沒結束
Nothing's over while I'm breathing.
我還挺希望你這麼說的
I kind of hoped you'd say that.
快點！
Come on!
嘿，傑克，背叛自己的種族是什麼感覺？
Hey, Sully, how's it feel to betray your own race?
你覺得你是他們中的一份子？
You think you're one of them?
該醒醒了
Time to wake up.
傑克？
Jake?
傑克
Jake.
傑克！我的傑克！
Jake! Ma Jake!
我看到你了
I See you.
外星人回到他們瀕臨滅亡的世界
The aliens went back to their dying world.
只有少部分人選擇留下來
Only a few were chosen to stay.
最痛苦的時候已經結束了
The time of great sorrow was ending.
他們不再需要圖靈騎士
Toruk Macto was no longer needed.
我想這是我最後一次影音記錄了
Well, I guess this is my last video log.
因為不管今晚發生什麼，我…
'Cause whatever happens tonight, either way, I'm...
我都不會回到這個地方
I'm not gonna be coming back to this place.
我想我最好走了
Well, I guess I'd better go.
對，我自己的聚會不能遲到
Yeah, I don't want to be late for my own party.
對，畢竟是我生日啊
Yeah, it's my birthday, after all.
杰克﹒沙力說再見了
This is Jake Sully signing off.